{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This corset-maker outlined his deist beliefs in The Age of Reason and condemned \"the summer soldier and the sunshine patriot\" in an attempt to raise support for the soldiers at Valley Forge. This author of The Crisis wrote \"these are the times that try men's souls.\" For 10 points, name this pamphleteer of the American Revolution who wrote Common Sense.",
      "answer": "Thomas Paine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Martial law was declared in Spain after an 1893 performance of this opera was bombed by anarchists. This opera's villain is the tyrannical Gesler, an Austrian governor of occupied medieval Switzerland. For 10 points, name this opera by Rossini in which Jemmy is instructed to \"Stay completely still\" before the title character shoots an apple off of his head.",
      "answer": "William Tell"
    },
    {
      "question": "Henning von Tresckow modified a plan for running the government if this event ever happened. Claus von Stauffenberg attempted to perform this action when he left a briefcase bomb under the target's desk in the Wolf Lair. For 10 points, name this never realized action that would have removed the head of the Third Reich.",
      "answer": "assassination of Adolf Hitler"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sidney Fox attributed this event to \"proteinoid microspheres.\" Svante Arrhenius was a subscriber to the \"panspermia\" theory, which holds that this process occurred due to the arrival of alien microbes. The Miller-Urey experiment concerned the formation of amino acids necessary for this process. For 10 points, identify this starting point of evolution on Earth.",
      "answer": "origin of life"
    },
    {
      "question": "A report on the state of these things was written by Julius Sextus Frontinus. One of these things used by the colony of Nemausus is part of the still-standing Pont du Gard. The Porta Maggiore incorporates two of these things, including the Anio Novus. Vitruvius recommended a low gradient for these things, which supplied public baths. For 10 points, name these constructs that carried water to Rome.",
      "answer": "Roman aqueducts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This book puts forth a three-phase \"salvation history\" of which the final phase is the Apostolic ministry. This book is attributed to the same author, an artist and physician, as the Book of Acts. This New Testament book is \"synoptic\" with Mark and Matthew. For 10 points, name this third book of the New Testament, a gospel which comes before John.",
      "answer": "Gospel/Book of Luke"
    },
    {
      "question": "Trygaeus (trig-EY-uss) flies a dung beetle to the gods to end this war in the play Peace. Several other plays blame Cleon (CLEE-on) for prolonging this war. Attempts to end this war with a \"sex strike\" are the subject of the play Lysistrata (LIE-siss-TRAH-tuh). For 10 points, name this war, opposed by Aristophanes (ah-riss-TAH-fuh-neez), in which Athens was defeated by Sparta.",
      "answer": "Peloponnesian War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A city in this state was praised for \"sewer socialism.\" This state is home to a university whose influence on government became this state's namesake \"idea.\" In 1924, over sixteen percent of American voters supported this state's Senator, the Progressive Presidential nominee Robert La Follette. For 10 points, name this state where Scott Walker was reelected in 2014 to the governor’s office in Madison.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Gorgas helped manage sanitation for this project, drawing on Walter Reed's research into yellow fever. The Hay-Banau-Varilla treaty cleared the way for this structure, which cuts through Gatún Lake. John McCain was born in its namesake Zone, which the US ceded in 1979. For 10 points, name this Central American waterway linking the Atlantic and Pacific oceans.",
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ended the Ingrian War with Russia by signing the Stolbovo. This member of the Vasa dynasty was succeeded on the throne by his daughter Christina. Known as the Lion of the North, this king was instrumental in the Protestant victory at Brietenfield before dying three years later at the Battle of Lutzen. For 10 points, name this Swedish king during the Thirty Years War.",
      "answer": "Gustavus Adolphus NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was heavily advised by future Pennsylvania Senator Arlen Specter. Its members included Allen Dulles and Hale Boggs, and it was criticized for advocating the \"magic bullet\" theory. This group was led by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court and concluded that Oswald acted alone. For 10 points, name this body charged with investigating the Kennedy assassination.",
        "answer": "Warren Commission"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Warren Commission viewed what clothing salesman's thirty-second home movie of the shooting?",
        "answer": "Abraham Zapruder"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man anticipated Ricardo's iron law of wages in his The Present High Price of Provisions. A modern disciple of this man's ideas is Paul Ehrlich. This man claimed that \"preventative checks\" such as birth control were the only way to avoid his namesake catastrophe. For 10 points, name this economist who predicted population would outstrip food supply.",
        "answer": "Thomas Malthus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Malthus was one of the few political economists to support what set of laws, which placed tarriffs on imported grain?",
        "answer": "Corn Laws"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man portrayed a defense attorney in Anatomy of a Murder. This man's roles in No Highway in the Sky and Flight of the Phoenix were inspired by his distinguished service as a pilot in World War II. With a frequent collaborator, he starred in Rear Window and Vertigo. For 10 points, name this star of four Alfred Hitchock films and It's a Wonderful Life.",
        "answer": "James \"Jimmy\" Stewart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1954, Stewart starred in a biopic about what trombone player and bandleader, who disappeared during World War II after being arguably the most popular musician of the early 40s?",
        "answer": "Glenn Miller"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A founder of this company is the namesake of a \"law\" stating that power doubles and price halves every eighteen months. This company purchased McAfee and Wind River and has been accused of using monopoly tactics against AMD. For 10 points, name this company which produces the Celeron, i7, and Pentium computer processors.",
        "answer": "Intel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Intel became the chief supplier to what company after it abandoned the PowerPC architecture in 2006?",
        "answer": "Apple"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the hub of the nahda cultural renaissance. Al-Fustat was absorbed into this city, where the Massacre at the Citadel was ordered by Muhammad Ali Pasha. In 969, this city became the Fatimids' capital, centuries before former slave soldiers called Mamelukes set up a sultanate here. For 10 points, name this pre-eminent city of Islamic Egypt which is the largest city by population in the Arab world today.",
        "answer": "Cairo, Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A luxurious \"long-staple\" variant of what inedible crop has been grown in Egypt since Muhammad Ali Pasha's rule?",
        "answer": "cotton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A painting by this man may be evidence that he had prior knowledge about the assassination of Julio Antonio Mella. After a painting by this artist was destroyed in New York for its controversial depiction of Vladimir Lenin, he repainted its subject as the “Controller of the Universe.” For 10 points, name this Mexican muralist of Man at the Crossroads.",
        "answer": "Diego Rivera"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rivera’s Man at the Crossroads was commissioned by which American family for their namesake center?",
        "answer": "Rockefeller family"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This current baseball team debuted as the White Stockings in 1870, and adopted its current name in 1907. This team reached the NLCS in 1984 and 1989 under the leadership of Ryne Sandberg, but failed to make the World Series. It is the oldest currently active Major League Baseball team, but the last of its 16 National League pennants came in 1930, and it hasn't won the World Series since 1908. For 10 points, name this Major League Baseball team that plays its games within the ivy-covered friendly confines of Wrigley Field in Chicago.",
        "answer": "Chicago Cubs"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which is the only current Major League baseball stadium that is older than the Cubs’ Wrigley Field?",
        "answer": "Fenway Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Journeys to this place are described in the Flatey Book. Karselfini clashed with residents of this place called \"Skraelings.\" An attempted colony in this place was discovered at the L'Anse aux Meadows site. A son of Eric the Red visited this place and dubbed it \"Vinland.\" For 10 points, name this continent visited by Leif Ericson nearly 500 years before Columbus's voyage.",
        "answer": "North America"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lief Ericson’s father Eric the Red helped settle what island, where the Lawspeaker presided over the Althing parliament?",
        "answer": "Iceland NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT EGYPT",
      "prompt": "Name the ancient egypt...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "lived around what river that flooded yearly?",
          "answer": "Nile River"
        },
        {
          "question": "served what ruler who was revered as divine?",
          "answer": "pharaoh"
        },
        {
          "question": "used what natural landform to bury New Kingdom royalty, including Tutankhamun?",
          "answer": "Valley of the Kings"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revered what domestic mammals as sacred to the goddess Bast?",
          "answer": "cats"
        },
        {
          "question": "lived north of what ancient region whose largest city was Meroë?",
          "answer": "Nubia"
        },
        {
          "question": "used what non-hieroglyphic script in the middle of the Rosetta Stone?",
          "answer": "Demotic"
        },
        {
          "question": "used what fermented beverage to pay scribes instead of cash?",
          "answer": "beer"
        },
        {
          "question": "played what 30-square board game whose rules, unlike mancala, are unknown?",
          "answer": "senet"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SPOILS SYSTEM",
      "prompt": "Name the spoils system...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Embraced by what Democratic President who succeeded John Quincy Adams?",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Also popular with Republican factions based in what city, the most populous in the U.S. since 1790?",
          "answer": "New York City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blamed for the death of what President in 1881?",
          "answer": "James Garfield"
        },
        {
          "question": "An expected source of patronage by what man who shot that President?",
          "answer": "Charles Guiteau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Particularly focused on what institution which oversaw tarriff collection at a busy port?",
          "answer": "New York Customs House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Severely curtailed by what 1883 \"civil service act?\"",
          "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opposed by what faction of Republicans who defected to Grover Cleveland in 1884?",
          "answer": "Mugwumps"
        },
        {
          "question": "Advocated by what leader of the Stalwarts and long-serving Senator in the 1870s?",
          "answer": [
            "Roscoe Conkling FOREIGN RELATIONS In",
            "with what foreign country did the United States…"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The founder of this group was arrested alongside Victor Tirado, after which he wrote From Prison, I Accuse the Dictatorship. Jaime Wheelock Roman led the “Proletarian Tendency” subgroup of this party. This group overthrow Anastasio (20 pts)",
        "Somoza Debayle, after which John Poindexter and Oliver North funneled money to groups (10 pts)",
        "opposing this party. For 10 points, name this Nicaraguan political party opposed by the Contras."
      ],
      "answer": "Sandinista National Liberation Front"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Archaeologists on this continent uncover bone \"projectile points\" made by the Clovis culture. \"Atlanteans\" are freestanding columns carved in the shape of warriors at Tula on this continent, where a circle called (20 pts)",
        "\"Woodhenge\" and Monks' Mound were in a large city made on raised earthworks at (10 pts)",
        "Cahokia. For 10 points, name this continent once home to the Mississippian culture, which was first settled by humans who crossed a land bridge across the Bering strait."
      ],
      "answer": "North America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was the subject of a synod convened by William Courtenay that was interrupted by an earthquake. Thomas Arundel persecuted this group. A member of this group, John Oldcastle, led a rebellion against Henry V. John of (20 pts)",
        "Gaunt protected the founder of this group. The name of this group may derive from a (10 pts)",
        "Dutch word for \"mumbler.\" For 10 points, name this proto-Reformation religious movement led by John Wycliffe."
      ],
      "answer": "Lollards"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This material was \"crimped and extruded\" to deal with traction problems. This material was originally called ChemGrass when it was invented by Donald Elbert for Monsanto in the early 1960s. This material was susceptible to intentionally bounced (20 pts)",
        "underthrows, perfected by Dave Concepcion. This material solved the problem of getting enough light to the inside of a (10 pts)",
        "Houston baseball stadium. For 10 points, name this pioneering artificial grass substitute."
      ],
      "answer": "Astroturf"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was speaking to a \"sewing society\" in Rochester when he asked \"What to the slave is the Fourth of July?\" This husband of Helen Pitts did not consent to his nomination as the (20 pts)",
        "Equal Rights Party's Vice-Presidential candidate on the Victoria Woodhull ticket. This survivor of the \"breaker\" Mr. Covey published The (10 pts)",
        "North Star and several autobiographies including My Bondage and My Freedom. For 10 points, name this anti-slavery orator."
      ],
      "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement's leaders included the president of the Morton Salt Company and retired general Robert Wood, then an executive at Sears. A prominent spokesman for this movement discredited it by denouncing (20 pts)",
        "Jews in Des Moines. This movement was unofficially supported by the (10 pts)",
        "German-American Bund. For 10 points, name this movement which moved from promoting neutrality to Nazi sympathy in the days before World War II, and included Charles Lindbergh."
      ],
      "answer": "America First Committee"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isabelle Falque-Pierrotin (FALK pee-ROH-tah), a French government official, has launched a campaign for global implementation of this legal privilege, which was first implemented in May 2014 after (20 pts)",
        "Mario Costeja (coh-STAY-hah) González's case was upheld by the (10 pts)",
        "European Court of Justice. For 10 points, name this right, unsuccessfully contested by Google, which allows an individual to have his or her name removed from search engine indexing."
      ],
      "answer": "\"right to be forgotten\""
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An all-night ritual at Bois [BWAH] Caiman preceded this uprising, whose leader turned on each other in the War of the Knives. The Code Noir oppressed the eventual victors of this war, such as (20 pts)",
        "Jean-Jacques Dessalines. Napoleonic troops in this conflict died of dysentery trying to save the largest coffee and (10 pts)",
        "sugar plantations in the Western hemisphere. For 10 points, name this slave revolt that ended Saint-Domingue, which Toussaint L'Ouverture led on the western side of Hispaniola."
      ],
      "answer": "Haitian Revolution NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}